I've talked a bit about computer properties and watchers.
We're going to have you go ahead and play around with that.
So for your exercise,
you'll have put a bunch of characters inside of your show.
So you probably have certain attributes that you
can put basically on those characters,
whether it's their age, height, whatever you want.
But then at those attributes to your characters,
and then use a computer property to start generating some sort of statistics.
So for example, mine is Avatar Last Airbender.
I could be like, okay,
two of them are water benders,
three of them are earth benders,
and then I can run computations on the percentage that might be.
So just have a play around with that.
It's one of those things where we'll be reusing a lot as we go forward.
So don't worry, you'll get plenty of opportunities to play around with that.
Welcome back everyone.
I hope that you found that exercise with
the computer property is fun to play around with.
But again, you'll get plenty of opportunity to practice that
because I think it's one of the features we need to use
more of and see more of in the ecosystem.
So definitely we'll be pushing that.
But during the exercise,
there was a great question regarding the differences between computed and watch.
Earlier in the example I showed,
you notice that the reason why I mentioned that the watch is not
a great technique in this particular case is
because you're dealing with the reactive data.
In other words, you're basically doing a computation that you're manually tracking.
This is not to say that watch as a technique is invalid however.
What that really means is that when it comes to computing data,
combining those things like we see up here with
optimized increment amount where you have multiple dependencies,
computed will do a lot of work for you right out of the gate.
So that's when you want to do that.
Anytime you're modifying something,
returning it and you want to be like,
I want to display something slightly different.
So actually the question earlier regarding the strings and combining them,
that would be an example where the character list,
for example, could be let's say, comma separated.
This is a bad name.
But you could do something like this.characterList.split.
You could do your calculation in here and then just return that in the render thing,
and that would already look good.
So I will show that later when we're doing it.
But the main point I want to make though is that watch is really
good for when you want to trigger a side effect on your code base.
So in other words, you can imagine if you might want to have
a specific API call when your reactive data has set a certain state.
That would be a great example of when
computed wouldn't make any sense at all because computed is about managing data.
Managing, triggering actions, that kind of stuff,
watch is perfect for that kind of stuff.
So just know that's the main paradigm difference
between the two when it comes to using them.
Okay. So let's take a look at this example.
So I'm going to go to my index to do the solution together.
Okay. So here, okay.
I got my characters here.
In this sign, let's add a property.
Let's call their element.
So I know that ng is air,
earth, water, and fire.
We won't get into SQL stuff for anyone who is an Avatar last airbender fan.
So we have fire.
We won't worry about stuff like lightning and metal bending for now, and water.
Okay. So here we have all of our stuff here,
and then for the sake of consistency,
let's just make sure we go and add an element here that's an empty array.
Great. Okay. So from here,
we could do some basically some statistics, shall we?
So for now, let's go ahead and actually add
a h2 here for just characters.
So this is consistent. There you go.
Characters up top, favorite characters, new character.
All right. And then actually just like I did before,
I'm going to go the most recent thing so that it's right at the top,
which is easier for people to see.
Let's talk about statistics.
So for something like statistics,
we want to figure out for example how many earth vendors we
have and then we have how many airbenders,
we have waterbenders, and then we have firebenders.
Okay. A couple of ways to do this,
but we'll start with the simple approach first,
which is that let's say we want to track the earth benders, right?
That was one of the ones I'd mentioned.
So let me hide data real quick.
So we're going to do a computed property because we're basically
just computing data off of what we already have.
So what we can do is we say earth benders.
Let's say earthbender list like that.
So return this.character list and we're going to filter it based on
every character and basically we want to know if,
actually let me do this a long way.
If character.element,
and then I realize there are more than one,
so I think it's not name right, but it's fine.
That element that I think contains should do the trick, earth.
Then we are just going to actually we'll do this one more.
Let's see. Return the filter.
Yeah. We can do it this way if it contains element earth,
and then return true,
and then we're returning the length of this thing.
So this is a little bit convoluted.
I want to go ahead and refract to this real quick.
So we can basically say that this contains the earth benders,
is what this filter does.
It goes through all the characters,
checks if they have it,
and if they have it, then it returns true.
So the easier way to actually write this is to return
since the logic is not complicated.
We can actually just do it like this.
One more. There you go.
So there we go, and then do,
do, do, do. Once we have earth benders,
we can return earth benders.
Oh, actually we could just return the list itself.
I'm actually overthinking this.
Okay. Here we go.
So to show that this actually does work,
I'm going to go ahead and render out the earth benders first.
So earthbender list, right.
If we were to frame,
oh, something broke,
contains, I miss, what is that?
Is it contains? Okay. That's fine.
That contains always throws me off.
Greater than negative one,
that should be, there we go, much better.
Okay. So we'll see here now is that it's gone
ahead and taken our list of characters,
and it's refined it down to the array
with only the characters that have like the earth element.
So this, again,
this is useful because then what we could do is we can say,
okay, well, then in this case we have like that length,
and there we go, we have the number of earth benders.
So you could basically duplicate this down as far as doing each one.
So I think though for the sake of making this a programmatic exercise,
we can just say, see bender statistics,
and rather than break it up each time,
we'll have, we know the list of elements we want.
So we have our elements,
which is going to be air, earth,
fire, and water.
So what we can do is then actually just do, do, do.
We're going to return an object where each of
these are going to contain like the updated value.
That way it's easier to display,
do, do, do, water, and do, do, do, fire.
Okay. Finally,
we will loop through every single element.
So this.characterList.forEach for every character,
and then do, do, do, do, do,
if do, do, do, do, elements.forEachElement.
If character.element.index of the naming on
this is going to be a little wonky,
and it's greater than negative one,
then we will say
const statistics equals this thing.
So actually, you know what?
I think I can do this one better.
We can actually do, do, do, do, do.
We can say statistics of the element plus equals one.
Do, do, do, do, yes.
So then we just need to make sure that is good.
Just like that, and then we return
set statistics. Okay.
That should do the trick.
I think, no wait, if this missing a parentheses.
Okay. I should do it.
Index of is still off.
Index of, oh, you're totally right.
Index of element, that's what was off.
Good call. Thank you.
Okay. Now let's give this a shot.
So we just render out the statistics now,
what I call bender statistics.
Then we could say,
for each is not liking it because I can't spell.
There we go. So we can see here there's one of each,
and the reason you get two here is because for those I don't know,
Aang has all the different elements,
so that's how we get that.
And you can see we have that computed property.
I see there's a question.
Should we use reduce here and pass
statistics object as a default parameter?
Reduce is certainly an option.
I just went with what was easier to do since I know
reduce can be confusing sometimes,
for those who don't use it a lot.
But reduce would be a great option in this point where we
could reduce the array and get the numbers that we want.
So, and for those who haven't used the reduce a lot in JavaScript,
reduce is pretty magical in that you can do
basically everything that you would want it to do,
but in that regard, the API can get a little bit complex sometimes.
So that's why I don't,
it's not my go-to when teaching these things.
So definitely a number of ways to do this.
To be clear, this is just like a quick code together of like,
how you could, you know,
cobble together the statistics,
but I'm sure there are many ways we could optimize for this.
But I just wanted to show that here,
now that we actually have everything,
we can show that we can
li and v4 through this bender list.
So I'll say stat in bender statistics.
And you'll see something interesting though,
is that if we just do this and just render out stat,
you'll notice here that it's only rendering out the right side.
And that's because, well, guess what?
We're in a for loop for an object and that's JavaScript.
So that means that if we want the key as well,
we need to actually just open it up because it's value then key.
So I would say type is probably what I would name that.
And then that way we can do type colon space,
refresh, there we go.
We have all elements and it's being computed as you would expect.
And so as you can imagine,
you can even extend on this to be like percentages and all that fun stuff.
And you just keep building on your computer properties.
And so what's nice about that because
computer properties can be composed,
it allows you to approach it in basically
kind of like a functional programming way.
You code the very small chunk that does this one computation,
then depend another chain on that.
And then that way you have actually a very clean like sort of
setup when it comes to managing those individual calculations.
So that said,
does anyone have any questions regarding what they just saw?